Mss.947.J82
American Philosophical Society
Journal of a campaign with the Russian army against Turkey, 1737-1739
Mss.947.J82
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 225 p.
This volume includes a journal of a campaign in Hungary (1737), and a diary (1738-1739) written in German.
1 volume, 225 p.
Crawford, John Lindsay,Earl of,1702-1749.
Volume 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from the library of Benjamin Franklin, 1803; accessioned, 1900.
Biographical/Historical note
John Lindsay, earl of Crawford and Lindsay (1702-1749), was a soldier. A Scotsman, he fought all over Europe. He was a captain in the British army and was permitted to join the Imperial army under Prince Eugene. In 1738 he received the rank of general from the Czarina Anna and fought against the Turks. He returned to the imperial forces and continued to fight until the Peace of London of 1748.
Related Archival Materials note
Lindsay's papers are continued in other manuscript volumes held by the APS: Account of some campaigns of the British army from 1689 to 1712 and a journal of a campaign under Prince Eugene on the Upper Rhine, 1689-1735 (Mss. 940 M68); Journal of a voyage from the Thames to Russia, and of campaigning with the Russian army, 1738-1739 (Mss. 947 L64).
Existence and Location of Copies note
Much of this volume, along with the other manuscript volumes of Lindsay's papers, were reproduced by Richard Rolt, Memoirs of the life of the Right. Hon. John Lindsay, Earl of Crawford and Lindsay (London: 1753).
Scope and Contents note
The maps in the volume were drawn by Henry Kopp, secretary and draughtsman for Lord Crawford. They are inscribed to George II, king of England; Lord Loudoun, etc.
The actual dates on which the maps were drawn is conjectural. These volumes were most probably prepared for Earl Crawford between 1743 and 1747 so they could be better seen and studied in the family's muniment room.
Early American History Note
This is one of four large volumes that were part of Benjamin Franklin's personal library. The four volumes comprise a series of John Lindsay Crawford’s travels with the Russian Army from 1737-1739. The volumes have large maps of Europe in them.
Beyond Early America; Diaries.; Hungary -- History -- 1699-1848.; Journals (notebooks).; Manuscript Essays; Maps.; Military History; Military maneuvers.; Military Records; Russia -- History, Military -- To 1801.; Russo-Turkish War, 1736-1739.; Travel Narratives and Journals; Turkey -- History, Military.
- Maps
  - Battle formation outside Pelegrad, 1743-1747; 1 map, 26.7 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Scope and Contents note
    Colored.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 29 (16).
  - Plan von der Ordre de Bataille wie solche bey Krozka den 30 Juny 1737, 1743-1747; 1 map, 36.2 x 24.1 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (17).
  - Lager bey Kollar, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.2 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (18).
  - Lager zwischen Kirsna und Losanitz, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.2 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (19).
  - Lager bey Lipoda, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.2 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (20).
  - Lager bey Lapova, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 35.6 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (21).
  - Battle formation (?) outside Pataschin, 1743-1747; 1 map, 26.7 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (22).
  - Battle formation outside Jagodina, 1743-1747; 1 map, 26.7 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (23).
  - Encampment, 1743-1747; 1 map, 25.4 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (24).
  - Lager bey Schapeljack, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.2 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (25).
  - Morara River near Zworneck, 1743-1747; 1 map, 19 x 26.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (26).
  - Lager bey Wresina, 1743-1747; 1 map, 23.5 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (27).
  - Gros Vizier Berg oder Konigsfeld, 1743-1747; 1 map, 25.4 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (28).
  - Fort, 1743-1747; 1 map, 26.7 x 20.9 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (29).
  - Town of Nissa (?), 1743-1747; 1 map, 23.5 x 36.2 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (30).
  - Road, 1743-1747; 1 map, 36.8 x 47 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (31).
  - Lager bey Pesniza, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.2 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (32).
  - Plan von der Palanka Krujowatz, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (33).
  - Lager bey Desternick, 1743-1747; 1 map, 25.4 x 20.3 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (34).
  - Feld Lager bey Ozaizack, 1737, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.2 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (35).
  - Feld Lager bey Lupit, 22 September 1737, 1743-1747; 1 map, 27.3 x 19.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (36).
  - Situation nebst der Palancka von Czazack, 1743-1747; 1 map, 26.7 x 20.9 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (37).
  - Lager bey Sabatz, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.2 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (38).
  - Plan der action zwischen Cornia and Carischa, 23 June 1738 - 4 July 1738, 1743-1747; 1 map, 88.9 x 40.6 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Attached is: Plan von der Schantze zu Mehadia. Colored.
    Realms of Gold, 29 (39).